Finding Aid for Werner Emmanuel Bachmann Papers, 1924-1951
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Werner Emmanuel Bachmann Papers 1924-1951
Bachmann, Werner Emmanuel, 1901-
3 linear feet
85475 Aa 2
Professor of chemistry at the University of Michigan. Correspondence; subject files; research notes and notebooks relating to cancer and penicillin research; teaching materials; reprints of writings; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was transferred from the U-M Dept. of Chemistry (donor no. 587. A smaller addition came from Mrs. Hampstead Bull (donor no. 6893 ) in 1983.
The collection is open to research.
Werner E. Bachmann was born in Detroit, Michigan, on November 13, 1901. After attending Detroit Junior College, Bachmann came to the University of Michigan where he received a BS degree in Chemical Engineering in 1923, an M.S. in 1924, and a Ph.D. in 1926. In 1925 he joined the faculty an instructor in organic chemistry, and remained at Michigan for his entire teaching career. He was promoted to Professor in 1939 and in 1947 was named the Moses Gomberg University Professor of Chemistry. Dr. Bachmann spent 1928 in Zurich, Switzerland, as a Rockefeller Foundation Fellow, and was a Guggenheim-Memorial Foundation Fellow in London and Munich during 1935-1936. In 1947 he returned to Switzerland for a lecture tour at the invitation of the American-Swiss Foundation for Scientific Exchange.
Among his many significant contributions were the first synthesis of a sex hormone, equilenin, and its stereoisoners, and the development of a new manufacturing process for RDX, a powerful explosive. His extensive research programs included work with carcinogenic compounds, antimalarials, and penicillin.
The papers, 1924-1951, of Werner Bachmann came to the library in three accessions. They consist mainly of correspondence with colleagues and students, papers relating to research and teaching activities, and a three volume set of bound reprints. The collection has been alphabetically arranged, with the exception of a folder of Mrs. Bachmann's correspondence, published works, a large certificate and photographs, which have been placed at the end. Of special interest are the papers relating to his research activities. There are notebooks and correspondence relating to cancer, equilenin, estrone synthesis, and penicillin research, as well as reports prepared by graduate students whose work was directed by Dr. Bachmann.
Subjects:
Cancer.; Chemistry.; Penicillin.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Chemistry.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Animal experimentation.; Bachmann, Werner Emmanuel, 1901-; Chemistry.; Classrooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Gomberg, Moses, 1866-1947.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Chemistry.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Alphabetical file
  - Bibliographies 1924-1949 (Box 1)
  - Biographical Material and Clippings (Box 1)
  - Certificates (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Undated 1924-1937 (Box 1)
      (scattered dates)
    - 1938-1939 (Box 1)
    - 1940-1942 1944-1946 (Box 1)
    - 1947 (Box 1)
    - 1948 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1949 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1949 (Box 1)
    - January-June 1950 (Box 1)
    - July-December 1950 (Box 1)
    - 1951 (Box 1)
  - Diary of year in Europe December 1928-1929 (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Papers (Box 1)
  - Notes on Problems, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Office of Scientific Research and Development
    - Anti-Malarials 1943 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1944-1946 (Box 1)
    - Penicillin 1945-1949 (Box 1)
    - RDX 1940-1950 (Box 1)
    - Reports 1945 (Box 1)
    - Summaries of Reports 1945 (Box 1)
  - Organic Division of the American Chemical Society 1939-1943, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Organic Reactions
    - Undated, 1939-1942 (Box 1)
    - 1943-1948 (Box 1)
  - Patents 1943, 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - Research
    - Cancer Research
      - Correspondence 1938, 1940-1941, 1944, 1947, 1949-1950 (Box 1)
      - Papers relating to work with J. Bradbury and M. Lewisohn 1936-1938, 1940-1941 (Box 1)
      - Research Institute or the Cancer Hospital, London (Notebook) 1935-1936 (Box 1)
    - Chemical Preparations (Notebook) 1928-1931 (Box 1)
    - Equilenin
      - Work with Cole and Wilds 1939-1940, 1942, 1946 (Box 2)
      - Work with Holmen 1947-1948, 1951 (Box 2)
    - Estrone Synthesis (work with Chin Chang) 1946-1950 (Box 2)
    - Fellowships
      - The Anna Fuller Fund
        - Correspondence 1938-1942 (Box 2)
        - Reports 1941 (Box 2)
      - du Pont 1937-1941 (Box 2)
      - Monsanto Chemical Company 1942, 1945-1946 (Box 2)
      - Rackham, Horace H., School of Graduate Studies
        - Correspondence and Papers 1939-1945, 1948 (Box 2)
        - Reports 1939-1944 (Box 2)
    - Penicillin (Notebook) 1944-1945 (Box 2)
    - Synthesis of Analogs of Sex Hormones (with Howard Siefen) 1943-1944, 1946, 1950 (Box 2)
    - Various Experiments (Notebooks)
      - 1928-1929, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1931-1934 (Box 2)
      - 1948 (Box 2)
  - Speaking Engagements
    - American Chemical Society 1939-1940, 1943-1948 (Box 2)
    - American-Swiss Foundation for Scientific Exchange 1946-1947 (Box 2)
  - Teaching Materials
    - Chemistry 53
      - Examinations 1945-1948 (Box 2)
      - Lecture Notes (Box 2)
      - Study Questions 1945-1946 (Box 2)
    - Chemistry 63
      - Examinations Undated, 1934 (Box 2)
      - Study Questions (Box 2)
    - Chemistry 65 (Examinations) Undated, 1929, 1933-1934, 1937-1941, 1943 (Box 2)
    - Chemistry 67
      - Examinations, Undated 1931-1933, 1935-1937, 1943-1948 (Box 2)
      - Lecture Notes (Box 2)
      - Study Questions (Box 2)
    - Chemistry 69 (Lecture Notes) (Box 2)
    - Chemistry 165 (Lecture Notes) (Box 2)
    - Chemistry 167
      - Examinations 1931-1935 (Box 2)
      - Lecture Notes, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Chemistry 169
      - Examinations Undated, 1927, 1931-1933, 1937, 1939-1942, 1944-1946, 1948-1949 (Box 2)
      - Lecture Notes (Box 2)
      - Study Questions (Box 2)
    - Chemistry 257
      - Examinations Undated, 1940, 1942-1944, 1946-1950 (Box 2)
      - Lecture Notes, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Chemistry 263 (Examinations) Undated, 1947 (Box 2)
    - Student Papers 1941, 1948-1950 (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous
  - Mrs. Bachmann (correspondence) Undated, 1943, 1949-1952 (Box 3)
  - Published Works
    - The Chemistry of Penicillin (Chapter XXII contributed by W.E. Bachmann and M.W. Cronyn) (Box 3)
    - Collected Works of W.E. Bachmann, 3 volumes (Box 3)
  - Membership certificate, National Academy of Sciences (Box 3)
  - Photographs, 2 envelopes (Box 3)